<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An Answer to A letter from a minister to a person of quality, showing some reasons for his non-conformity</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1679</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 53 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A25527</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3317</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R15207</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11925251</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11925251</idno>
            <idno type="VID">51006</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A25527)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 51006)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 48:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An Answer to A letter from a minister to a person of quality, showing some reasons for his non-conformity</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Blythe ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1679]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Place and date of publication from NUC pre-1956 imprints; printer information from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Yale University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:51006:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:51006:1"/>
            <head>AN ANSWER TO A LETTER. FROM A Miniſter to a Perſon of Quality, ſhewing ſome Reaſons for his Non-Conformity.</head>
            <p>AMongſt the many Licencious Papers, which Seditious and Deſigning men in this preſent and ſad Juncture of Affairs ſo induſtriouſly ſpread abroad, I find one with this Title, <hi>A Letter from a Miniſter to a Perſon of Quality, ſhewing ſome Reaſons for his Non-Conformity;</hi> and ſhould admire how a Perſon of thoſe moderate Pretenſions as <hi>A. B.</hi> (if I miſtake not my Initial Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters) hath for theſe ſeveral years affected to be eſteemed, ſhould chuſe to appear in ſuch Company. But that as it begins to be viſible, this ſeems to him and others of the ſame Leven, to be the time to unmask themſelves, and ſhew that they are ſtill true to the <hi>Solemn League and Covenant,</hi> which how tender ſoever they are of renouncing it, yet were not at all ſo when they had Power (or rather Force) to impoſe it. But an intended Reformation and Purity of Religion muſt anſwer all Pleas, and with <hi>Jehu</hi> they doubt not to call in others to ſee their zeal for the Lord, though it be as his was in ſlaying his Maſter. And 'tis not ſo far out of the memory of Man, to charge them with having done that once, and to implore the Divine Goodneſs that it may never be in their Power (I doubt 'tis too much in their Wills) to do it again. However I cannot but mind them, that theſe were the ſame Scruples of Non-Conformity which prepared their Conſciences for it; and let men diſpute matters as they pleaſe, let them with <hi>Hazael</hi> when the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet wept, becauſe of <hi>the evil he knew he would do the children of Iſrael, that their ſtrong holds he would ſet on fire, and their young men would ſlay with the ſword, and would daſh their children, and rip up their women with child;</hi> let them (I ſay) with <hi>Hazael</hi> receive their rediction of their Barbarities with the Indignity he did, <hi>viz. Are we dogs that we ſhould do this great thing?</hi> 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 8.11, 12, 13. Yet there is nothing can more probably convince them to be ſuch, than their preſent <hi>barking;</hi> and I heartily pray God it may not too ſoon come to <hi>worrying the flock.</hi> 'Tis the <hi>Shepherd</hi> alas they at preſent run ſo fierce at, but the <hi>Sheep, Fleece,</hi> and <hi>Fleſh</hi> too, muſt not expect to be free from their ravenous Jaws. <hi>Experti loquimur:</hi> and this I am bold to charge upon the Zeal of theſe men, who according to the account <hi>S. Paul</hi> gives of ſuch, ('twould be too ſevere to tranſcribe their whole Character, let them that are at leiſure peruſe it, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.2, 3, 4, 5.) <hi>creep into houſes, and lead captive ſilly women laden with ſins, led away with divers luſts.</hi> Onely I could hope better of the <hi>Perſon of Quality,</hi> whoever ſhe be, to whom he pretends to direct his Letter, and as to one of whom I have ſuch hopes, I ſhall preſume to dedicate this following <hi>Reply;</hi> beſeeching her and all true Chriſtians, that they henceforth be no more <hi>children, toſs'd to and fro, and carried about with every wind of doctrine, by the ſleight of men, and cunning craftineſs, whereby they lie in wait to deceive, Eph.</hi> 4.14. that as 'tis in the foregoing Verſe, they would ſeriouſly bethink themſelves, that the way to come <hi>unto a perfect man, unto the meaſure of the Stature of the fulneſs of Chriſt,</hi> is to be in the <hi>unity of the faith;</hi> and as the Apoſtle adjures them by all the names and motives of kindneſs, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.1, 2, 3. that muſt be by doing nothing <hi>through ſtrife or vain glory:</hi> which did men really lay aſide, could they at ſuch a time as this eſpecially, when the Religion of Chriſt is in ſo great jeopardy, then the Proteſtant Faith lies at ſtake, and we know not how ſoon our Candleſtick may be remov'd, (I am <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e we have Enemies enough to attempt it, and what is worſe, Sins enough to deſerve it) open the breach <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>der, and pride themſelves in increaſing the Confuſion? This, <hi>Madam,</hi> is what I cannot but recommend <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>our ſerious thoughts, and leave it to your own Conſcience to make the judgment whether had <hi>A. B.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap>r weight of Arguments than I hope to make appear he hath, it had been (I will not ſay pious, but) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="7 letters">
                  <desc>〈7 letters〉</desc>
               </gap>ble, to blow that Coal, that cannot but give new warmth to the common Adverſary, and increaſe
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:51006:2"/>his Pleaſure in ſeeing his Plot thrive by our Counſels, and our ſelves both confounded by it. <hi>Madam,</hi> I cannot but ſpeak my Fears; I cannot but naturally dread that the ſame Cauſes ſhould have the ſame Effects. How much <hi>Rome</hi> hath already triumph'd in our Diviſions, (nor doth it heal our breach, that they have as great ones among themſelves) our late Troubles are too ſad an Inſtance; and that they are carrying on the ſame Deſign, that 'tis all one to them whether we fall by their or our own hand, (nay this is the more glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous effect of their Subtilty) we need make no doubt at all. Nor can it be any Aſperſion or Calumny, to load our Diſſenting Brethren with this <hi>Odium,</hi> when 'tis eaſie to prove, that in all their Diviſions and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diviſions, from the Presbyterian, Independent, Anabaptiſt, Fifth Monarchy Men, down to the Quaker, the Prieſts and Jeſuits of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church have been the Engins on which all their dangerous Counſels have ſtill moved; and ſo eaſie a thing is it for theſe <hi>Deceivers</hi> to transform themſelves back again into what they were, before they appeared under theſe Vizors, that I muſt confeſs 'tis what I have often thought, and ſaid to thoſe I have convers'd with, that <hi>Rome</hi> can never ſucceed in <hi>England,</hi> but under the Mask of Non-Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity. That conſidering (to do our ſelves that right) we are in our Temper and Climate a ſerious religious People, there can never be any Method ſo ſuccesful for the <hi>Factors of Rome,</hi> as to bring us over to themſelves, by teaching us to faſten the name of <hi>Papiſt</hi> upon the <hi>conſcientious Conformiſt,</hi> by crying down the <hi>Church of England</hi> under the name of being <hi>Popiſhly inclin'd,</hi> though ſhe be indeed the <hi>onely Bulwark</hi> to defend us from it. The Church which the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> above all dread and oppoſe, as moſt ſure to ſuch Principles, as can never ſtoop to her Errors. And if it be a <hi>fault,</hi> that with reference to that <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> which is neither found among the Papiſts or Non-Conformiſts; if it be a <hi>crime,</hi> that we cannot but be Loyal to our Prince, that we cannot but live in charity towards our Neighbours, that we cannot but deſire that our Religion in the publick Offices of it ſhould be intelligible, neither in an unknown Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage with the Papiſts, nor as the uncertain ſound of the Trumpet in the <hi>ex tempore</hi> Effuſions of the Non-Conformiſts. If it be a <hi>fault,</hi> that no Pretence of Grace can teach us to Out men of their lawful Inheritan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that nothing can tempt us to Sacrilege, things from which I wiſh either Papiſt or Non-Conformiſt could clear themſelves. If they that cannot ſwallow a Steeple either with the Spire downward, leſt it ſhould prick their Conſcience; nor with the Tower, leſt the Weather Cock ſhould appear at top, and ſhew how the wind blows; as I think the Story is faſten'd on <hi>A. B.</hi> Yet ſhall make no ſcruple of ſwallowing Church and Church Land: nay if they are not belied, have already divided the ſpoil, and taken into their <hi>poſſeſſion the houſes of God,</hi> not conſidering that (as the Pſalmiſt expreſſes it, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 83.13.) God hath already once made them like <hi>a wheel, and as the ſtubble before the wind;</hi> that they are not yet ſo ſure of the time, but that <hi>the wheel</hi> that lifts them up may bring them down. If I ſay the contrary things to what I wiſh they were not guilty of, be our <hi>unpardonable crimes,</hi> we muſt, we cannot but own and glory in our Infirmities.</p>
            <p>But that I may not any longer detain your Ladyſhip from a <hi>particular Reply</hi> to the Letter, which I profeſs to dedicate to you, as the <hi>Miniſter</hi> doth his, leaving it to your impartial judgment to determine of the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons he offers for his <hi>Non-Conformity,</hi> which he grounds upon, as he calls them, <hi>Three grand Declarations re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quir'd to be made by all thoſe who will conform: the firſt concerning the Book of Common Prayer, the ſecond con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning taking up Arms againſt the King, the third concerning the Solemn League and Covenant; with reference to all which,</hi> ſaith he, (<hi>eſpecially the firſt and laſt</hi>) <hi>I have had hitherto inſuperable Objections againſt the making any ſuch Declaration.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in all theſe I ſhall follow him ſtep by ſtep, in what he objects and argues againſt them. Onely I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but obſerve the Pomp in which he dreſſes his Scruples; and that though one of them be againſt the very Fundamentals not onely of ours but all Government, I mean that of <hi>Taking up Arms againſt the King;</hi> which in truth, is to make good the Lawfulneſs of the <hi>Solemn League and Covenant,</hi> 'tis neceſſary he ſhould aſſert, The <hi>Covenant</hi> in its nature and deſign, and as 'twas applied and made uſe of by the firſt Contrivers of it, having a direct tendency to Rebellion; and for them that inbottom upon Rebellion in the State, to profeſs and defend Schiſm in the Church, is but ſuitable to the Synod's Principle of Diſobedience, from whom both proceed. This being obſerv'd, I now go on to trace him in the diſtinct Paragraphs of his Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, in the third of which he ſets forth, that the firſt Declaration concerning the Book of Common Prayer is to be made in theſe very words, <hi>viz. I</hi> A. B. <hi>do declare my unfeigned aſſent and conſent to all and every thing contained and preſcribed in and by the Book, entituled, The Book of Common Prayer and Adminiſtration of the Sacraments, and other Rites and Ceremonies of the Church, according to the uſe of the Church of</hi> England; <hi>to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the Pſalter or Pſalms of</hi> David, <hi>pointed as they are to be ſung or ſaid in Churches; and the form or man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of making, ordaining, and conſecrating of Biſhops, Prieſts, and Deacons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Madam,</hi> here is required <hi>aſſent and conſent,</hi> yea <hi>unfeigned aſſent and conſent;</hi> and that it may be is one of his chief Scruples that he may not prevaricate with Authority, were there allow'd but a little Equivocation in the caſe, and the Diſſenter permitted to give an <hi>aſſent and conſent</hi> which were not unfeigned, the Task had not been ſo intolerable; but to require ſuch an <hi>aſſent and conſent</hi> as thus ſearches men to the bottom, and beats the Hypocrite out of all his Subterfuges, who can bear it? And that not onely in this Book of Common Prayer, but in the Book of God it ſelf: for ſo he argues in the fourth Paragraph, telling us, <hi>That he queſtions whether many a ſober man would not ſcruple to declare ſo much concerning any copy of the Bible now ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant in the world in any language whatever, even the Originals themſelves not excepted, which by tranſcribing may have their faults, and therefore every thing contained in them not to be unfeignedly aſſented and conſented unto.</hi> But to ſee then on how weak a foundation his Argument ſtands, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. That to <hi>aſſent and conſent to all and every thing contained and preſcribed in and by this Book, &amp;c.</hi> is to <hi>aſſent and conſent to any Errata or faults that may eſcape in the tranſcribing the true copy.</hi> 'Tis (I confeſs) a new way of reaſoning, and ſuch as I think a man of underſtanding cannot be in the leaſt guided by; for by that means there's nothing in the world, the moſt undoubted Articles of our Faith, and unqueſtion'd Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentals of Religion, (I need give no other Inſtance than himſelf doth in the Bible which contains theſe) that ought to be <hi>aſſented and conſented</hi> to: but 'tis trivial to inſiſt on ſuch a Cavil, and therefore I ſhall leave this to every man to conſider with himſelf, whether in matters of another nature, and of the moſt weight
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:51006:2"/>concern in this World, ſuch as our <hi>Lives</hi> and <hi>Fortunes;</hi> we do not think we may ſafely <hi>aſſent,</hi> and <hi>conſent</hi> to the <hi>contents</hi> of any writings that paſs <hi>an Eſtate,</hi> confirm <hi>our Liberties</hi> and <hi>Properties,</hi> unleſs we likewiſe ſubſcribe to the <hi>Errata,</hi> which in the frequent copying out, and tranſcribing the <hi>Records,</hi> or <hi>Enrolled Deeds</hi> may happen; 'tis abſurd to call thoſe <hi>Errata</hi> the contents of ſuch writings, and if they were ſo, yet neither would ſuch a ſcruple affect us here, becauſe to what is contain'd is added likewiſe what is <hi>preſcrib'd in and by the Book,</hi> and unleſs <hi>A. B.</hi> can ſhew that the <hi>Errata</hi> are likewiſe preſcrib'd in and by the Book, that there is ſome Rubric to confirm them, his Argument (I am aſham'd to give it that name) will be alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether Captious and Nugatory. Again,</p>
            <p n="2">2. He inſinuates that for any perſons to require <hi>aſſent</hi> and <hi>conſent</hi> in this manner is to ſuppoſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves <hi>Infallible,</hi> this is the ſum of his <hi>5th Paragraph.</hi> But how odious an inference is this, and how de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive of the Reaſon of <hi>all Laws?</hi> Muſt not by this Argument every <hi>Lawgiver</hi> be ſuppos'd to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible, the end of all whoſe injunctions are to be aſſented and conſented to; and if Men refuſe to yield the obedience requir'd, they know, and are to abide by the Puniſhment or Sanction of the Law, and yet never any yet urged that againſt their Laws. And is it any more that is done here, we require not this <hi>aſſent</hi> and <hi>conſent</hi> from all that will be <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> the <hi>Declaration</hi> reaches not Men in their private capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city, but only ſuch as ſhall deſire to come into any public <hi>charge in the Church;</hi> and if it be neceſſary there ſhould be a Rule for Uniformity (they thought ſo I am ſure who devis'd and impos'd their <hi>Directory</hi>) 'tis neceſſary that Men ſubſcribe to it, ſubſcribe to it not as an abſolute <hi>Rule of Conſcience,</hi> but as a <hi>Rule of Peace</hi> and <hi>Order;</hi> and this is all the <hi>Church</hi> requires that they ſo far ſubmit their <hi>Will</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding</hi> to their Governors, as for theſe ends, to conform to what they have preſcrib'd. Nor doth a Man <hi>violate his Conſcience,</hi> who if there be nothing <hi>ſinful</hi> in the thing requir'd, ſhall ſubmit to what is preſcrib'd, although it may not altogether ſuit with the meaſure of his inclination or Judgment: No not though he doth this with the moſt <hi>unfeigned aſſent and conſent,</hi> becauſe unfeign'd Aſſent and Conſent, what ever his Paraphraſe on theſe words imply to the contrary, doth not ſuppoſe every thing ſo required to be <hi>aſſented and conſented to,</hi> to be in the higheſt degree of perfection, but to be ſuch as for the great <hi>Ends</hi> aim'd at, he can <hi>freely</hi> and <hi>truly</hi> comply with; ſuch wherein he dares not, at leaſt will not, advance <hi>his private Sentiments</hi> above the <hi>deliberate Acts,</hi> and conſtitutions of thoſe whom God hath ſet over him, and whom 'tis his duty to obey in <hi>indifferent things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And is it any more than this that we profeſs, notwithſtanding his cavil at it, that 'tis our firm perſuaſion that there is nothing in the whole Book contrary to the <hi>Word of God,</hi> or to <hi>ſound Doctrine,</hi> or which a <hi>Dodly man may not uſe, or ſubmit unto with a good Conſcience. Now though this be our perſuaſion, yet</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>'tis not every Man's perſuaſion, and therefore unreaſonable to force others to the ſame profeſſion:</hi> Upon this Reaſon no Law can be of force, becauſe there is nothing ſo <hi>good,</hi> ſo <hi>pious,</hi> ſo <hi>uſeful,</hi> but ſome may not be of the <hi>perſuaſion</hi> that 'tis ſo, nay 'twould be unreaſonable to require either the <hi>belief of a God,</hi> or obedience <hi>to any moral precept,</hi> becauſe ſome may have been found ſo <hi>Atheiſtical</hi> as to deny the one, and ſo <hi>profligate</hi> as to diſown the other. But to ſee then what is the ſtrong Reaſon he backs this with, <hi>viz.</hi> with thoſe words of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> Rom. 14.22. <hi>Haſt thou Faith, have it to thy ſelf;</hi> i. e. in his Gloſs, <hi>force it not upon others, compel them not to think as thou thinkeſt, believe as thou believeſt, declare as thou declareſt; ſtudy thine own and thy neighbours peace better, and the rather becauſe thou are a fallible Creature, and mayſt be in an Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror as well as any other.</hi> Now I would ask our <hi>ſcrupulous Nonconformiſt,</hi> whether that Rule be given to the <hi>public Officers</hi> in the Church, or the <hi>private Chriſtian?</hi> If to the <hi>private Chriſtian,</hi> it concerns not our Caſe, if to the <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> or <hi>public Officers</hi> in the Church, why then is there a Rule laid down by him otherwhere, to <hi>reject the Heretic,</hi> Titus 3.10. Are any, at leaſt do any pretend to be ſo firmly <hi>perſuaded</hi> of what they hold <hi>as the Heretic?</hi> Is not <hi>obſtinacy</hi> the conſtant concomitant of all their Opinions? Or why <hi>is every Soul commanded,</hi> in the preceding Chapter <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1. <hi>to be ſubject unto the higher Powers,</hi> why are they that <hi>reſiſt the Power, ſaid to reſiſt the Ordinance of God,</hi> and told further, that they <hi>ſhall receive to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Damnation?</hi> Why <hi>v.</hi> 5. is it farther continu'd, and that upon the Reaſons added <hi>v.</hi> 3, 4. <hi>that they muſt needs be ſubject not only for wrath,</hi> but <hi>alſo for Conſcience ſake?</hi> What, I ſay, is the meaning of this, with what is farther preſt in that whole Chapter, if all is to be preſently blown away with <hi>our having Faith to our ſelves,</hi> to <hi>our ſelves too</hi> in the ſenſe that thoſe Men too often have it, that they will allow it to be no where but in their <hi>Conventicles,</hi> no where but in that <hi>Separation,</hi> which St. <hi>Jude</hi> tells us, <hi>v.</hi> 19. <hi>is ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual, having not the Spirit.</hi> How is the Conſcience concern'd in our Obedience, if nothing in no ſence may be required from us to believe or declare: If becauſe the Magiſtrate <hi>is a fallible Creature, and may be in an Error as well as any other,</hi> he muſt <hi>ſtudy his and his neighbours Peace better than to force his Faith,</hi> to what in his Conſcience he thinks beſt for the Subject, why are there then any public Sanctions in the World? Why is not every thing <hi>iniquity,</hi> that is <hi>decreed by Law?</hi> Men might be aſham'd of this Reaſoning, eſpecially when if they do but remember what they did in their own Trials of the Abilities and Capacities of Miniſters to be receiv'd into the Church, 'twas not then <hi>haſt thou Faith, have it to thy ſelf;</hi> no 'twas ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary the Probationer ſhould be able to give an account of the moſt ſecret workings of his Faith, of the beginning and progreſs of his Converſion, as though every one who is born of the Spirit be as the Wind, that <hi>bloweth where it liſteth, and we may hear the ſound thereof, but cannot tell whence it cometh, and whither it goeth,</hi> John 3.8. they ſearch'd ſo deep, were ſo blaſphemous, and Sacrilegious, as to take to themſelves the place of God <hi>to ſearch the Heart, and to try the Reins,</hi> and be ſatisfied with none for their Candidates, but the <hi>Godly and Regenerate:</hi> nay, and when Men came up to all their <hi>Marks of Tryal,</hi> yet if there were not one more of being of their <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Party,</hi> they might indeed have their <hi>Faith to themſelves,</hi> without any hopes of being approv'd and accepted by their ſanctified Triers. This was then the <hi>Liberty of Conſcience</hi> they gave, This indeed their <hi>Tyranny</hi> beyond that of <hi>Egypt</hi> or <hi>Babylon.</hi> And the complaint they now have is, that the <hi>Laws of the Land</hi> (all which they then violated in the groſs, and I fear long for the ſame <hi>happy Toleration</hi>) and the <hi>Governors of the Church</hi> in obedience to thoſe Laws, require their Compliance to what, as to the matter of it, as <hi>A. B. himſelf Par.</hi> 7. confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:51006:3"/>
               <hi>he hath nothing to ſay againſt it.</hi> And <hi>Par.</hi> 6. <hi>I would to God they had requir'd no more in Conformity, than <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe and Submiſſion:</hi> that is, that men ſhould uſe and ſubmit to the Liturgy. And what more is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired? I am very confident did they uſe the Liturgy in their Meetings, did they recommend Conformity to it to their Followers, though they had never declar'd their Aſſent and Conſent, Authority would never have concern'd it ſelf to repreſs them. Although 'tis inexcuſable to ſay, There is nothing they can ſay againſt the Liturgy of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> that they can uſe and ſubmit to it, and yet not be willing to declare the ſame. Nay, is not ſuch a Confeſſion more than any Declaration, becauſe whatever man may declare for the outward Peace of the Church, yet the confeſſing of the things to be declar'd is the voice of Conſcience, and ſuch an Acknowledgment as I doubt they will not find a Salve for, <hi>when the ſecrets of all mens thoughts ſhall be made known.</hi> I wiſh they would timely conſider, what 'tis by their Example and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to hold back ſo many poor Souls from doing what they dare not ſay is unlawful! what 'tis more than once, (pray God the Ferment the Nation at preſent is in, do not work it ſelf into it!) I ſay more than once to have kindled a Rebellion! They may think what they will of Succeſs, the Booty and Reward of proſperous Miſchief, yet will it not be <hi>bitterneſs in the end?</hi> and can thoſe men that hold out the Argument, perſons moſt of them who were actually engaged in the laſt Troubles, and moſt of them men of Years, think, that ſhould they eſcape the Violence they ſtir up, it cannot be long e're Nature would call upon them to give an account (how comfortable an account let them conſider) to ſay no worſe. I would ſpeak as charitably as I can of their miſtaken Zeal. But 'tis our Zeal too they are offended at, that beyond what our preceding Governours did with reference to this Book of Common Prayer, we thus ſtrictly enjoyn, that Miniſters do declare their <hi>unfeigned aſſent and conſent.</hi> All that they required being, <hi>That it ſhould be read and uſed, and the Rites and Ceremonies of it to be duly obſerv'd.</hi> And was that all they requir'd, and yet could they then find in their hearts to riſe up againſt ſuch Meekneſs and Lenity? Or is not the Caſe very different from what it then was? Are not the Men we have to deal with, thoſe who were gone off from all Obedience to Church or State, and is it not reaſon we take ſome Pledge of them for their future Integri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty? Is any man found guilty of a much leſs heinous Indictment, and yet diſcharged without giving Sureties for his Behaviour? If there were nothing elſe, 'tis neceſſary men ſhould ſhew their actual repentance, in what they have actually offended. Shall men who have broken through Oaths of Allegiance to their Prince, and of Canonical Obedience to their Dioceſans; men who have ſubſcribed the Canons and Articles of the Church, and have prevaricated in both; men that gave the early Teſt of what they were driving at, as (we are not without Inſtances of this nature before the breaking out of the laſt Civil War) to require, when called to it, in order to their Degrees in the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities,</hi> that they might <hi>Subſcribe</hi> in their own Sence? Shall I ſay, ſuch men be diſpleas'd, if we cannot take the <hi>Viper</hi> into our breaſt, without pulling out the <hi>Sting,</hi> that we dare not admit men of theſe <hi>Principles</hi> and <hi>Practiſes,</hi> to come into the <hi>Church,</hi> without giving ſuch Caution of their being in good earneſt, as may juſtifie thoſe in admitting them who have the care of the public, and ſhould be very bad <hi>Paſtors of Chriſt's Flock,</hi> ſhould they knowingly receive <hi>Wolves</hi> inſtead of <hi>Sheep</hi> intot he Fold. Although when all the Care is taken that can be, I doubt not, ſome ſuch there will be, ſome ſuch whom theſe men teach to be <hi>Hypocrites,</hi> in ſo ſerious a Profeſſion, as that of a <hi>Miniſter,</hi> thoſe, I mean, whom they pity in their <hi>Conformity,</hi> as doing what they would not do, if they were not forced to it. Alas, <hi>good men,</hi> 'tis the reſtraint that is upon them makes them do what they do, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as a <hi>Shiboleth</hi> to their party, how do they <hi>Curtail</hi> the Prayers? With what <hi>Negligence</hi> and <hi>Oſcitency</hi> do they read what they do not curtail, forgetting that whatever they may think, <hi>God</hi> will not be mocked, 'tis his <hi>Name</hi> is called upon, his <hi>Spirit</hi> is preſent, and cannot but judge the falſhood of ſuch a Heart: How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, theſe are the <hi>men</hi> that do their <hi>work:</hi> theſe are they whom they countenance among us, and theſe, whom we cannot but be aſhamed of, and compaſſion the poor miſguided people, who are taught to look upon thoſe as Holy and Godly Men, who thus profeſſedly offer the <hi>Sacrifice of Fools.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to follow <hi>A. B.</hi> in his Argument, he proceeds (<hi>Parag.</hi> 8.) to explain what is meant by <hi>Aſſent and Conſent; Which</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>with reference to the party aſſenting relates to his underſtanding; and with reference to the thing aſſented to, relates to the truth and rightfulneſs of it. And with reference to the party conſenting, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates to his will; and with reference to the thing conſented to, relates to the goodneſs, expediency, and behoofulneſs of it. According to which Action</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>when I declare my unfeigned aſſent to all and every thing contained in, and preſcribed by the Book of Common Prayer, 'tis as to what is true and right, and not to the leaſt error in it from top to bottom, not in any Rite or Ceremony, not in the form and manner of making, ordaining, and conſcrating Biſhops, Prieſts, or Deacons, no not ſo much as in pointing the Pſalms, or in any other tittle or circumſtance. So again, when I declare my unfeigned conſent, &amp;c. it is as if I had declared, That I heartily and cordially cloſe in, and chuſe every thing mention'd and preſcrib'd in the ſaid Book as good and expedient, as moſt eligible and behooful to be done, practiſed, and obſerv'd. And this is the reaſon,</hi> he adds, <hi>why he dares as well eat hot fire coals, as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare his unfeigned aſſent and conſent, &amp;c. becauſe many things are therein contain'd and preſcrib'd which he deems ſcarce right and true,</hi> (however right and true he doth deem them) <hi>much leſs good and expedient to be done and embrac'd.</hi> To which in ſumme I anſwer as above, that 'tis not neceſſary to the <hi>aſſent and conſent</hi> here requir'd, that every particular perſon ſhould take upon him expreſly to determine in all theſe Points; 'tis ſufficient that nothing is ſinful: much leſs doth it become his Humility to oppoſe the Opinion he hath of a thing's being good and expedient, to the Senſe and Reaſon of his Governours; 'tis matter of Obedience belongs to him, and it little avails whether he thinks it expedient, as long as thoſe to whoſe Judgments he hath as much reaſon to incline as to his own, eſpecially in a thing that himſelf dares not ſay is <hi>ſinful,</hi> though he think it ſo. But to weigh what the things are which he ſcruples, and pitches onely upon two or three, <hi>viz.</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>The Order of reading the holy Scripture, Parag. 9.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>The Order of Miniſtration of Baptiſm.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>The Order of the Burial of the Dead.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list> And with theſe he concludes his Paper, <hi>Parag.</hi> 19.</p>
            <p>Now to examine how far theſe are real and juſt Scruples of Non-Conformity.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:51006:3"/>
            <p>Firſt, As to <hi>the Order of reading the holy Scripture, Parag. 9.</hi> the Exception is, becauſe <hi>many Books of the Apocrypha are commanded to be read, and ſome Books of the ſacred Canon are wholly left out; ſome of them but part to be read, ſome of them curtail'd and mutilated, as to the ſeveral Chapters contained in them.</hi> Where I cannot but obſerve a very different Zeal in <hi>A. B. Paragr.</hi> 4. he had ſaid, That <hi>he queſtions whether many a ſober man would not ſcruple to declare his Aſſent and Conſent, concerning any Copy of the Bible now extant in the World, in any Language whatſoever, even the Orginals themſelves not excepted, becauſe by tranſcribing it may have faults.</hi> I am very glad to find him now ſo concern'd for the <hi>holy Scripture,</hi> and there's no honeſt Church of <hi>England</hi>-man, who will not joyn with him in it. Only we deſire that our Governours be not blamed, if according to their beſt diſcretion they have choſen out ſuch parts of Scripture to be read in the Congregation, which are moſt <hi>intelligible,</hi> if they omitted others, ſuch as many Chapters of the <hi>Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicles</hi> and <hi>Revelation</hi> are, which they thought would not be for the <hi>Edification</hi> of a vulgar Auditory: And if they have mixed ſome of the <hi>Apocrypha,</hi> they are withall ſuch parts of it, as may be of wholſom Inſtruction, and for their equailing theſe with the holy Scripture, properly ſo called, 'tis ſufficient that 'tis in our <hi>Articles</hi> declared, what Books we look upon as <hi>Canonical,</hi> what as <hi>Apocryphal,</hi> and that we neither diſguiſe, nor recommend either, but under their proper Names: And whether this be a Reaſon to break <hi>Communion</hi> with a <hi>Church,</hi> let any man Judge, eſpecially ſince 'tis no new thing to recommend Books that are not Scripture to be kept, and expoſed in the Church to public uſe, ſuch as <hi>Eraſmus</hi> his Paraphraſe, <hi>Foxe</hi>'s Martyrology, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and yet theſe are not ſcrupled at.</p>
            <p>His next Scruple is,</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Againſt the Order appointed for the Miniſtration of Baptiſm,</hi> and that upon theſe three accounts.
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Becauſe of Godfathers and Godmathers.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Becauſe of the Croſs.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>Becauſe of what is annexed to the end of the Sacrament.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>I. He doth not approve of <hi>the ſtrict requiring of Godfathers, and Godmathers, to ſtand as Sureties, and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndertakers for the Child to be baptized,</hi> viz. <hi>That he ſhall renounce the Devil, and all his Works, and conſtantly believe God's holy Word, and obediently keep his Commandments.</hi> But whether <hi>A. B.</hi> approve them or no, I can ſhew him thoſe that did approve them very early in the Church, and that the common Conſent of the whole Church, both Eaſtern and Weſtern, hath ever ſince run along with that Practice. But to weigh his Reaſons, and thoſe of ſuch moment, that they are ſufficient with him, as I juſt now obſerv'd, to juſtifie his deſerting the Communion of the Church; for,
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Becauſe it is unſcriptural.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Becauſe in the interim the Father of the Child is left out.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>Becauſe Godfathers and Godmothers are generally brought to the Font to avouch a great untruth, and make themſelves obnoxious of lying, and perjury in the Face of God and the Church.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>To the firſt, that tis <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nſcriptural:</hi> 1. 'Tis not neceſſary it ſhould be mentioned in Scripture, 'tis ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient if the Practice of the Church confirm it, and it be not againſt the <hi>Rule</hi> or <hi>Analogy</hi> of Scripture. Beſides; 2. It cannot be ſuppos'd it ſhould be preſcribed in Scripture, the receiving of <hi>Perſons</hi> by <hi>Baptiſm</hi> there, being upon their own <hi>actual Faith,</hi> and before there was any <hi>conſtituted national Church,</hi> wherein this <hi>Order</hi> could be obſerv'd, and 'twas ſufficient that the <hi>Children</hi> were admitted then to <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> as they were into the <hi>Covenant,</hi> that is, by the Faith of the <hi>Parents;</hi> which is the Reaſon why they are now capable of the <hi>Ordinance;</hi> and were the taking in of Godfathers only <hi>abundans cautela,</hi> 'tis the firſt time that any deſerted a Church, becauſe it took the beſt Care it could of its Members. Nor is it rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable in the ſecond place,</p>
            <p n="2">2. To Object, <hi>That in the interim the Father of the Child is left out,</hi> when the receiving the Child ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the <hi>Father</hi> concern'd in it, becauſe 'tis through his <hi>Faith</hi> he is in the Covenant, and as to his parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular ingaging for the Child's Education, he muſt be worſe than an <hi>Infidel,</hi> if he do not take care for <hi>thoſe of his own Houſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">3. Much leſs can it bear any weight with conſidering men, that he inſinuates, <hi>The Godfathers and God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothers being generally brought to the Font to avouch a great untruth, and make themſelves obnoxious of lying, and perjury, in the Face of God, and the Church:</hi> Becauſe if they are guilty of this, this is their <hi>abuſe,</hi> of what is well intended, and that can no more make againſt the having <hi>Godfathers and Godmothers</hi> for the Child, becauſe tis poſſible they may neglect their <hi>Duty,</hi> than it doth againſt <hi>Baptizing the Child</hi> at all, becauſe he may not anſwer the intents and purpoſes of that <hi>Solemn Vow,</hi> or of admitting the Father him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to be a Sponſor in this caſe, becauſe he may be careleſs in the matter. Beſides, not to admit God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers and Godmothers, might in ſome caſes be totally to debar the Child of Baptiſm, becauſe it may ſo fall out that the Father may be dead before the Child is born, and then how ſhall he be offered to Baptiſm?</p>
            <p>And as for <hi>A. B</hi>'s Suppoſition, that <hi>A Parent ſhould tax his Goſſips with their neglect, and the great miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief accruing to the Child upon that very account,</hi> doth he not much more tax himſelf, who ſhall make ſuch an Argument againſt this practice, which can ſignifie nothing, if he do but diſcharge his own Duty? How fallacious a concluſion is it, becauſe men neglect their Duty, therefore they are not to be engaged in it!</p>
            <p>II. And <hi>then as to his Reaſoning againſt the Croſs, Par.</hi> 13. 'tis ſo trifling, that I wonder with what Face any can urge it, <hi>viz.</hi> Becauſe whereas 'tis ſaid, <hi>We receive this Child into the Congregation of Chriſt's Flock, and do ſign him with the ſign of the Croſs, in Token hereafter he ſhall not be aſhamed to confeſs the Faith of Chriſt crucified, &amp;c.</hi> Now, ſaith he, this word <hi>In token</hi> is to him a meer <hi>Riddle;</hi> 'tis much it ſhould be ſo, there being no word of a more vulgar uſe, and implies as much as <hi>a ſign of Remembrance,</hi> which is the very ſence to which 'tis here applied, Only he hath a ſence to wreſt it to, in which he knows the Church of <hi>England</hi> never took it, and therein he gives a mighty Proof of his Charity, that he cannot <hi>joyn in Communion</hi> with the Church of <hi>England,</hi> leſt ſome other of <hi>leſs underſtanding</hi> than himſelf ſhould miſtake
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:51006:4"/>the ſence of <hi>one word</hi> in the Liturgy: 'tis I confeſs an extraordinary ſort of Zeal, to make anothers <hi>want of Judgment</hi> the meaſure of my Religion. But there's a farther deſign in that, than every one obſerves, put a falſe gloſs upon the Text, and then condemn it of Hereſie, miſinterpret the words, and impeach the Church of the ill conſequences. But what then is it we muſt ſpell out of this mighty Niceneſs? <hi>I am,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>apt to believe the generality may much miſtake it</hi> (miſtake it then it ſeems they muſt, before they can misjudge it) as if when it is ſaid <hi>in Token,</hi> it had been ſaid <hi>In Virtue and Power of this Sign;</hi> another man it may be would be apt to believe that they could not thus miſtake it, it being altogether Foreign from the uſe of the word ſo to underſtand it. But 'tis all one, put the rub in the way, that you may be ſure not to loſe your pains in proving 'tis neceſſary it ſhould be removed. For my part, I cannot tell how any thing but an induſtrious love of miſtaking could have given him that ſence of the word, and indeed, who beſides himſelf ever ſo underſtood it? Did the Ancient Fathers plead ſo much for it in any other ſence than Chriſt commanded his Diſciples, to take up their Croſs and follow him? Are they to imitate their Maſter in doing this in the whole courſe of their life, and may they not ſo much as uſe a <hi>Sign</hi> to expreſs it to others, or to bring them in mind of their Duty themſelves?</p>
            <p>Was not the Croſs, the name, and reproach of it, that which deterr'd ſo many from the early pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Chriſt's Religion, and is it now an improper Symbol, whereby to confeſs themſelves not aſhamed of it? Or are Signs leſs lawful, than words to imprint the ſame?</p>
            <p>'Tis frivolous to ſay, <hi>'tis too like a Sacrament upon a Sacrament thus to add the ſign of the Croſs to Baptiſm,</hi> becauſe the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> never ſo explained it, no, ſhe is at pains to explain it otherwiſe, and give the juſt Reaſons for retaining it in the <hi>30th</hi> Canon firſt publiſh'd, <hi>Anno,</hi> 1604. However, this will not excuſe <hi>A. B</hi>'s expreſſion in the beginning of <hi>Par.</hi> 12. where he ſays, <hi>That the baptizing the Perſon</hi> ipſo facto, <hi>exhibits a Virtue and Power, to every worthy partaker of it, to fight againſt Sin, the World, and the Devil,</hi> this I ſay will not excuſe his expreſſion from <hi>looking too</hi> like the <hi>Sacrament's conferring Grace, ex opere operato,</hi> which had any but a zealous Non-conformiſt ſaid, He would not have eſcaped the imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Popery.</p>
            <p>What is continued, <hi>Par.</hi> 13. <hi>That though Chriſtians in the Primitive times might uſe the Croſs, yet the very ſame Reaſons which might put them upon that uſe with a reference to the Heathens, ſhould now move them wholly to diſuſe it, with a reference to the Papiſts, becauſe what profeſſors then did, was to diſtinguiſh them from Pagans, who ſcorned the Croſs, with every Token and Sign of it,</hi> (it ſeems the word <hi>Token</hi> is not ſuch a meer Riddle, but <hi>A. B.</hi> can underſtand and uſe it) <hi>and by Parity of Reaſon we ſhould now forbear ſo doing, to diſtinguiſh our ſelves from the Idolatrous Papiſts, who ſuperſtitiouſly adore the Croſs, fooliſhly, fondly, and wickedly ſigning themſelves with it upon every Occaſion.</hi> But if they abuſe what the Primitive Chriſtians ſo Religiouſly uſed, why ſhould not we rather reſtore it to its right uſe? Or if their Abuſes muſt aboliſh the thing, then why don't we part with our Baptiſm too, becauſe 'tis the Ceremony with which they admit into the Church, and do ſo much corrupt the uſe of it?</p>
            <p>III. His third exception, <hi>Againſt Order uſed in the Miniſtration of Baptiſm,</hi> is, becauſe <hi>of what is annexed to the end of the Sacrament,</hi> viz. <hi>It is certain by God's word, that Children which are baptized dying before they commit actual Sin, are undoubtedly ſaved. Par.</hi> 14. <hi>I would,</hi> ſaith <hi>A. B. they had quoted the place, for I confeſs mine own ignorance, that I know no ſuch word in Scripture:</hi> But what then, may not that be certain by God's word, that is not there <hi>in terminis?</hi> Is there no ſuch thing as the Analogy of Faith, as the collecting, and inferring any thing from Scripture (and that which is ſo, is certain by God's word) which is not laid down there in Propoſition? May it not be according to the <hi>Tenour of God's Word,</hi> becauſe 'tis not found there in ſo many Syllables, that <hi>Children which are baptized dying before they commit actual Sins, are undoubtedly ſaved.</hi> What think we of St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s telling us, 1 <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 3.20, 21. Where ſpeaking <hi>of thoſe that were ſaved in</hi> Noah's <hi>Ark by Water,</hi> he ſubjoins the like <hi>Figure</hi> whereunto even <hi>Baptiſm doth alſo now ſave us,</hi> and <hi>Mark</hi> 1.4. is not Baptiſm ſaid to be <hi>for the Remiſſion of Sins,</hi> ſuch it is in it ſelf, ſuch it cannot but be to thoſe that rightly partake of it, and if Children do this, if by this they are actually brought into the <hi>Covenant of Grace,</hi> whil'ſt they break no Law, as 'tis only by <hi>Actual Tranſgreſſion</hi> they can do this, is it any queſtion that they are undoubtedly ſaved, that is, put at leaſt into a <hi>Salvable condition?</hi> I ſhall not need to add that Chriſt ſaith of ſuch, <hi>i. e.</hi> of <hi>little Children</hi> that come to him, and 'tis <hi>by Baptiſm only</hi> that they can come, is the Kingdom of Heaven. What he fills his 15 <hi>Par.</hi> with, concerning <hi>the Children of wicked Parents, who are yet baptized, and many of them dye imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately after baptiſm, is a moſt unreaſonable and uncharitable inference,</hi> becauſe to put the Child <hi>in Covenant,</hi> 'tis not neceſſary the Parent be any more than an <hi>Outward Profeſſor</hi> of the true Religion, <hi>'twas ſo with the</hi> Jews, <hi>it muſt be ſo with the</hi> Chriſtians: And as for what he infers from the ſecond Commandment, <hi>which,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>gives ſome ſcruple to his Faith,</hi> viz. <hi>of God's puniſhing the Iniquity of the Fathers upon their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, to the third and fourth Generation,</hi> hath been always interpreted upon Suppoſition of their <hi>continuing in the Sins of their Fathers,</hi> and 'twas upon the Jews erring in this point, which their Proverb of <hi>the Father's eating the ſower Grapes, and the Children's Teeth being ſet on edge,</hi> that God himſelf is at pains to rectifie the miſtake, and lay it down as an Eternal Truth, That <hi>the Soul that Sins ſhall dye,</hi> that <hi>the Child ſhall not bear the Iniquity of the Father,</hi> Ezek. 18.</p>
            <p>His Suppoſition of <hi>a Chriſtian King's conquering a Country of Pagans, Mahometans, and Jews, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelling all their Infants forthwith to be baptized, and ſome of them expiring before they have committed actual Sin, Par.</hi> 17. is wholly remote from the Queſtion, the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> ſuppoſing ſuch only as are the proper <hi>Subjects of Baptiſm.</hi> And for his <hi>merciful Butchering Infants,</hi> as he continues his Suppoſition, <hi>Par.</hi> 18 <hi>before they have committed actual Sin, that ſo without any father hazard, they might have the Poſſeſſion of Eternal life,</hi> 'tis impious to ſuggeſt, and blaſphemous from hence to argue the <hi>Power of any mortal wight over Souls,</hi> becauſe he can be the Inſtrument to <hi>Baptize,</hi> and then to <hi>kill the poor Infant,</hi> becauſe ſhould this be admitted, 'tis not he that Baptizes, but God that gives the Title by his Baptiſm to Heaven, and its not to be doubted but many a wicked Villain hath been the Inſtrument to ſend a Martyr to Glory. I am
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:51006:4"/>ſure the Church hath always thought moſt charitably of thoſe Innocents <hi>Pilate</hi> murdered; and 'tis to be doubted, thoſe who are ſo keen and bitter againſt them, would not argue as they do, had they but ſome of the Meekneſs and Humility of Children.</p>
            <p>His <hi>18th Par.</hi> falls under the Anſwer we gave to his <hi>16th Par.</hi> To conclude this head therefore, What is, or is not in the power of man is not the Queſtion, but rather what is the End, and deſign of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, what the Uſe for which 'tis preſcrib'd, what the ſence God himſelf hath put upon it.</p>
            <p>That <hi>Odium</hi> he would load the Miniſter with, <hi>That ſhall deny to Adminiſter Baptiſm to them, who come not according to the Rule of the Church, or to queſtion whether it would be Baptiſm or no, to pronounce the Form over the Child of an unbelieving Parent,</hi> are beſides our Argument, 'tis ſufficient that he hath no Title ſo to do it, that he is more ſerious in his Function than to be knowingly unjuſt, either to the Truſt, the Church, or God himſelf, as I may ſay, hath repos'd in him.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The laſt ſcruple with which he ſhuts up his Paper, is, with reference to <hi>the Order for the Burial of the Dead,</hi> particularly that Paſſage of it: <hi>For as much as it hath pleaſed God of his great mercy to take unto himſelf the Soul of our dear Brother here departed, we therefore commit his Body to the Earth,</hi> &amp;c. I have only this to ſay, that 'tis in the Judgment of Charity we pronounce this, of all, That ſome there are of whom we may ſay it in great aſſurance of their happy Tranſlation, that 'tis not neceſſary the words <hi>in great mercy</hi> ſhould refer to the perſons taken away, for it may be mercy, and great mercy to them who ſuffer'd by their Injury, or ill Examples, ſuppoſing them to be ſuch, in which no ſhew of Godneſs did appear. Beſides, I do not think, that when I give my <hi>Aſſent and Conſent,</hi> it is neceſſary it ſhould reach the ſence of the words any otherwiſe than they relate to their proper ſubjects; ſome there are, of whom this may, and ought to be ſaid, and 'tis a poor Cavil againſt the Communion of a Church, that her Offices are framed to ſuit thoſe who are her real Members. Nor have I ever thought the Perſon officiating, obliged to uſe this Form of Burials intirely in all Caſes; nor that it had been however either neceſſary, or Chriſtian, to preſcribe another, indeed it had been a Contradiction, becauſe 'tis ſuppos'd to be Chriſtian Burial we give by it, and however this be generally us'd, yet 'tis well known, there are thoſe to whom ſhe denies her Office of Burial, and ſomething I conceive may even in lower Caſes be left to the diſcretion of the Prieſt, eſpecially with the Advice of his Ordinary: In a word, the Church provides for thoſe that ought to have Chriſtian Burial, and thoſe to whom it doth not belong, are not the ſuppos'd Subjects of this Office.</p>
            <p>What he concludes all with of our adding in the Collect, that <hi>when we ſhall depart this life, we may reſt in him, as our hope is this our Brother doth,</hi> is, what hath no inſuperable Objection in it, there being none ſo bad, but for whom we ought to hope the beſt: The Thief upon the Croſs, we know, found mercy, and what may be the dealings of God with the moſt profane wretch in the laſt minute? What may be the Temptations he hath had to encounter? What his Tryals we know not: We ſee the <hi>Fall,</hi> but cannot tell what his <hi>Wreſtlings</hi> were. And therefore which is the ſureſt, the moſt Chriſtian way, that the Church chalks out, and I am ſure we have reaſon to rejoyce, that we are of a Church whoſe Charity is extenſive, and I pray God, our diſſenters never give us Occaſion to forfeit that Character; that if they have the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs they boaſt, they would exerciſe ſome of it as towards thoſe who in all their contradictions, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but pray for, and pity them; ſo towards thoſe poor Souls they have hitherto ſeduced, and cannot but know, that whatever their pretences are, why themſelves do not conform, yet they can never anſwer it to Almighty God, that they ſo ſhut up the Kingdom of Heaven againſt men, as <hi>neither to go in themſelves, nor to ſuffer them that are entering to go in, Matth.</hi> 23.13. To whom amidſt all their long Prayers, their Zeal to compaſs Sea and Land to make <hi>Proſelytes,</hi> their Nice diſtinguiſhing of the lawfulneſs of an Oath, whil'ſt themſelves live in the avow'd defence of Perjury. For ſuch is their ſolemn League and Covenant taken, and perſiſted in againſt that Oath of Allegiance, which they have, or ought to take to their lawful Prince, and urged as a reaſon why they cannot conform. Their exactneſs in paying (as I may ſay) Tythe of Mint, Aniſe, and Cumin, in being preciſe in leſſer things, whilſt they omit the weightier Matter of the Law, Judgment, Mercy, and Faith, Obedience to their juſt Superiours, Charity to thoſe that live in greater ſtrictneſs of Life than themſelves; their making clean the outſide of the Cup and Platter, with the likeneſs they too much bear to whited Sepulchers, I ſhall only leave them to conſider how far what is ſo often denounced by Chriſt, <hi>Matth.</hi> 23. may concern them, <hi>viz. Woe unto you Scribes, and Phariſees, Hypocrites.</hi> And now, Madam, I cannot but conclude with this ſhort Caution to you, and all others, whom <hi>A. B.</hi> and his Brethren, are the Occaſion, either by their Words, or Example of with-holding from Conformity, That you would ſeriouſly conſider what 'tis to live in Diſobedience to your lawful Governours, eſpecially in thoſe things which <hi>A. B.</hi> himſelf tells you he can ſay nothing againſt, <hi>Par.</hi> 7. conſider who 'tis hath told you, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.23. that <hi>Rebellion is as the Sin of Witchcraft, and Stubborneſs is as Iniquity and Idolatry.</hi> There's nothing ſo oppoſite to the Rules of Morality, and Religion, to the Worſhip, and acknowledgment of a God, and his Providence (for all this is implied in Witchcraft, Iniquity, and Idolatry) as Rebellion, and Diſobedience to lawful Governours in their lawful Commands, and God knows like Idolatry, and Witchcraft, nothing with which fooliſh Men are ſo much bewitch'd, no Idol equal to that of their own Brain, the Inventions, and Imaginations they ſet up to themſelves: God in his Mercy to this tottering Nation forgive, and prevent the miſchievous Deſigns of thoſe Sons of <hi>Belial,</hi> who are now carrying on both in Church, and State, and open the Eyes of all the truly conſcientious, to ſee the things belonging to their Peace, even in this their day: There ſeems ſtill to be a day, and a price put into our hand, if we have the heart to make uſe of them, God forbid we ſhould be ſuch Fools to neglect the opportunity: I am ſure if we be, no Apology we can make, will clear us from being <hi>of the Plot</hi> againſt our Religion, and Country; if we muſt fall (I ſpeak it to all good Subjects, all good Chriſtians, and amongſt them I conjure <hi>A. B.</hi> and his Brethren, as they will anſwer it at the day of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, when the ſecrets of all Hearts ſhall be laid open) yet let not our ſelves contribute to it, let not that be the fatal Complaint, <hi>Thy deſtruction was of thy ſelf O</hi> England.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:51006:5"/>
            <p>Madam, this is what ſo few hours leiſure, as I have had to peruſe <hi>A. B</hi>'s Letter, and return a Reply to it, would allow me to rejoyn to his Objections, againſt <hi>the firſt Declaration, concerning the Book of Common Prayer,</hi> and as he goes on with his Scruples againſt the <hi>ſecond,</hi> and <hi>third Declaration, viz.</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Taking up Arms againſt the King, and the Solemn League and Covenant,</hi> I ſhall endeavour, through God's Bleſſing, to find time to reſolve them, if not with much hopes of doing good on their Leaders, (alas! men that act with deſign, and are fond of ſetting up themſelves againſt Authority, are not ſo eaſily converted) yet of reducing ſome of thoſe honeſt, well-meaning Souls, whom they have led aſtray, nor do I ask God's Bleſſing upon my Labours, any farther than he, who knows all Hearts, knows that what I write is out of an intire Love of his Religion, and Truth, in which I am</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your real, and faithful Servant,</hi> &amp;c.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Printed for JOHN BLYTHE, at Mr. <hi>Playford</hi>'s Shop in the <hi>Temple.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
